Oliver was an extremely dashing,
كان أوليفر جذاب للغاية
handsome, charming and largely unstable male
فهو ذكر وسيم، ساحر وغير اعتيادي
that I completely lost my heart to.
حتى أني وقعت في حبه تماماً
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
He was a Bernese mountain dog,
إنه كلب من فصلية البرمية الجبلية
and my ex-husband and I adopted him,
والذي قمت أنا وزوجي السابق بتبنيه،
and about six months in,
وبعد مضي ستة أشهر،
we realized that he was a mess.
أدركنا أنه فوضوي جدا.
He had such paralyzing separation anxiety
كان يعاني من قلق الإنفصال المعيق
that we couldn't leave him alone.
فلم نكن قادرين على تركه لوحده.
Once, he jumped out of our third floor apartment.
ففي إحدى المرات قفز من الطابق الثالث.
He ate fabric. He ate things, recyclables.
كان يأكل المنسوجات. كان يأكل أشياء، المواد القابلة للتدوير.
He hunted flies that didn't exist.
كان يلاحق حشرات غير موجودة،
He suffered from hallucinations.
حيث كان يعاني من التهيؤات.
He was diagnosed with a canine compulsive disorder
تم تشخيصه بأنه مصاب باضطراب الكلاب القهري
and that's really just the tip of the iceberg.
وهذا كان جزء بسيط جداً من معاناته
But like with humans,
لكن كما هو حال البشر،
sometimes it's six months in
بعض الأحيان تمر ستة أشهر
before you realize that
قبل أن تستوعب أن
the person that you love has some issues.
الشخص الذي تحب لديه بعض المشاكل.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And most of us do not take the person we're dating
معظمنا لا يعيد الشخص الذي يواعده
back to the bar where we met them
إلى المكان الذي التقى به فيه
or give them back to the friend that introduced us,
أو إلى الشخص الذي عرفه عليه
or sign them back up on Match.com.
أو يعيد تسجيله في match.com
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
We love them anyway,
نحن نحبهم بأية حال
and we stick to it,
ونتشبث بتلك العلاقة.
and that is what I did with my dog.
وهذا ما فعلته مع كلبي.
And I was a — I'd studied biology.
كنت قد درست الأحياء
I have a Ph.D. in history of science
أحمل درجة الدكتوراه في تاريخ العلوم
from MIT,
من معهد ماساتشوستس للتقنية
and had you asked me 10 years ago
ولو سألتموني قبل عشر سنوات
if a dog I loved, or just dogs generally,
إن كان الكلب الذي أحبه، أو الكلاب عموماً
had emotions, I would have said yes,
لديها مشاعر، كنت سأجيب بنعم،
but I'm not sure that I would have told you
لكن غير متأكدة من أنني سأخبركم
that they can also wind up with an anxiety disorder,
أنه من الممكن أن يصابوا بإضطراب القلق
a Prozac prescription and a therapist.
ويحتاج إلى وصفة بورزاك، ومعالج نفسي.
But then, I fell in love, and I realized that they can,
ولكني أحببته، وأدركت إمكانية حدوث ذلك،
and actually trying to help my own dog
وفي الواقع، محاولتي مساعدة كلبي
overcome his panic and his anxiety,
على تجاوز ما يصيبه من قلق ونوبات هلع
it just changed my life.
غيرت حياتي.
It cracked open my world.
فتحت عالمي بشكل كلي
And I spent the last seven years, actually,
حتى أني قضيت آخر سبع سنين
looking into this topic of mental illness in other animals.
أتعمق في دراسة الأمراض النفسية لدى الحيوانات الأخرى.
Can they be mentally ill like people,
هل يمكن أن تكون مريضة نفسيا،
and if so, what does it mean about us?
وإن كان كذلك، ماذا يعني ذلك لنا؟
And what I discovered is that I do believe
الشيء الذي اكتشفته هو أني أعتقد
they can suffer from mental illness,
بإمكانية إصابتها بأمراض نفسية،
and actually looking and trying to identify mental illness in them
ومحاولة تحديد الإضطراب النفسي لديها
often helps us be better friends to them
تساعدنا لنتعامل معها بطريقة أفضل
and also can help us better understand ourselves.
وتساعدنا أيضاً على فهم أنفسنا بشكل أفضل.
So let's talk about diagnosis for a minute.
لنتحدث عن تشخيص المرض لمدة دقيقة.
Many of us think that we can't know
الكثير منا يعتقد أنه لا يمكننا أن نعرف
what another animal is thinking,
ما الذي يفكر فيه حيوان آخر
and that is true,
وهذا صحيح،
but any of you in relationships —
لكن أي منا لديه علاقة--
at least this is my case —
على الأقل في حالتي أنا--
just because you ask someone that you're with
بمجرد سؤالك ذلك الشخص
or your parent or your child how they feel
أو أحد والديك، أو طفلك عن شعوره
doesn't mean that they can tell you.
لا يعني أنه قادر على التعبير عن شعوره.
They may not have words to explain
من المحتمل أن لا يجد كلمات ليعبر بها
what it is that they're feeling,
عن شعوره المكنون.
and they may not know.
ومن المحتمل أنه لا يعرف ما يشعر به.
It's actually a pretty recent phenomenon
وهذه ظاهرة معاصرة نوعاً ما
that we feel that we have to talk to someone
وهي الشعور بحاجتنا للحديث مع أحد ما
to understand their emotional distress.
لفهم محنته العاطفية.
Before the early 20th century,
قبل بداية القرن العشرين الميلادي،
physicians often diagnosed emotional distress
كان الأطباء غالباً يشخصون المحنة العاطفية
in their patients just by observation.
لدى مرضاهم عبر الملاحظة فقط.
It also turns out that thinking about
كذلك، يتبين أن دراسة
mental illness in other animals
الأمراض النفسية لدى الحيوانات
isn't actually that much of a stretch.
ليست بعيدة في الواقع.
Most mental disorders in the United States
أكثر الاضطرابات النفسية في الولايات المتحدة
are fear and anxiety disorders,
هي الخوف واضطرابات القلق،
and when you think about it, fear and anxiety
وعندما تفكر بالأمر، الخوف والقلق
are actually really extremely helpful animal emotions.
هما في الحقيقة من أكثر مشاعر الحيوانات فائدة.
Usually we feel fear and anxiety in situations that are dangerous,
عادة ما نشعر بالخوف والقلق في الأوضاع الخطرة
and once we feel them,
وحالما نشعر بهذه المشاعر
we then are motivated to move away
نتحفز لنبتعد
from whatever is dangerous.
عن كل مصدر للخطر.
The problem is when we begin to feel fear and anxiety in situations that don't call for it.
تكمن المشكلة عند شعورنا بالخوف والقلق في حالات لا تستدعي ذلك.
Mood disorders, too, may actually just be
اضطرابات المزاج، كذلك، يمكن أن تكون
the unfortunate downside of being a feeling animal,
الجانب السلبي المؤسف في كون الحيوان ذات مشاعر،
and obsessive compulsive disorders also
وكذلك اضطراب الوسواس القهري
are often manifestations of a really healthy animal thing
غالبا ما يعكس جانب حيواني في حالة جيدة.
which is keeping yourself clean and groomed.
كأن يهتم بالنظافة والمظهر.
This tips into the territory of mental illness
كل هذا يدخل تحت ما يسمى بالمرض النفسي
when you do things like
عندما تقوم بتصرفات مثل
compulsively over-wash your hands or paws,
الإفراط في غسل اليدين أو القدمين القهري،
or you develop a ritual that's so extreme
أو أن تتبنى عادات أو طقوس متطرفة
that you can't sit down to a bowl of food
حتى أنك لن تستطيع الجلوس لأكل الطعام
unless you engage in that ritual.
حتى تنغمس بأداء تلك العادات والطقوس.
So for humans, we have the "Diagnostic and Statistical Manual,"
بالنسبة للبشر، لدينا كتاب "Diagnostic and Statistical Manual"
which is basically an atlas
وهو عبارة عن دليل
of the currently agreed-upon mental disorders.
يتضمن كل ما اتفق عليه من إضطرابات نفسية.
In other animals, we have YouTube.
أما بالنسبة للحيوانات الأخرى فلدينا موقع يوتيوب
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
This is just one search I did for "OCD dog"
هذة نتيجة لبحث عن "كلاب مصابة بالوسواس القهري"
but I encourage all of you
وأنا أحثكم جميعاً
to look at "OCD cat."
لتبحثوا عن "قطط مصابة بالوسواس القهري".
You will be shocked by what you see.
ستصابون بالصدمة مما ستجدون.
I'm going to show you just a couple examples.
سأقوم باستعراض بعض الأمثلة.
This is an example of shadow-chasing.
هذا مثال على مطاردة الظل.
I know, and it's funny and in some ways it's cute.
أعلم، هذا مضحك وبشكل ما لطيف أيضاً.
The issue, though, is that dogs can develop compulsions like this
المشكلة أن الكلاب يمكن أن تكتسب مثل هذه العادات
that they then engage in all day.
ثم تنغمس في ممارستها ليوم كامل.
So they won't go for a walk,
حتى أنها لن تخرج للنزهة،
they won't hang out with their friends,
ولن تلتقي بأصدقائها،
they won't eat.
وقد تمتنع عن الأكل.
They'll develop fixations
ستنشأ لديهم عادات ثابتة
like chasing their tails compulsively.
مثل مطاردة الذيل بشكل قهري.
Here's an example of a cat named Gizmo.
هذا مثال لقط اسمه جيزمو.
He looks like he's on a stakeout
يبدو أنه يراقب شيئاً
but he does this for many, many, many hours a day.
لكنه يفعل هذا لمدة ساعات عديدة كل يوم.
He just sits there and he will paw and paw and paw
يجلس هناك، يضرب بيده مراراً وتكراراً
at the screen.
على شرائح الستارة
This is another example of what's considered
وهذا مثال آخر على ما يعرف
a stereotypic behavior.
بالسلوك النمطي.
This is a sun bear at the Oakland Zoo named Ting Ting.
هذا دب في حديقة حيوانات أوكلاند اسمه تينق تينق
And if you just sort of happened upon this scene,
لو مررتم مروراً عابراً على هذا المشهد
you might think that Ting Ting
كنتم ستظنون أن تينق تينق
is just playing with a stick,
يلعب بالعصا ليس إلا،
but Ting Ting does this all day,
لكن تينق تينق يفعل هذا طوال اليوم،
and if you pay close attention
ولو دققتم أكثر
and if I showed you guys the full half-hour of this clip,
أو عرضت لكم الشريط الكامل لمدة نصف ساعة،
you'd see that he does the exact same thing
سترون أنه يكرر نفس التصرف بالضبط
in the exact same order, and he spins the stick
بنفس الترتيب، وهو يلف العصا
in the exact same way every time.
بنفس الطريقة كل مرة.
Other super common behaviors that you may see,
أحد أكثر أنواع السلوك شهرة والتي يمكن أن تلاحظ
particularly in captive animals,
خاصة لدى الحيوانات المحبوسة في أقفاص،
are pacing stereotypies or swaying stereotypies,
هي أنماط سلوكية مثل العدو والتمايل،
and actually, humans do this too,
وفي الحقيقة، حتى البشر يمارسون ذلك،
and in us, we'll sway,
مثلاً نقوم بالتمايل،
we'll move from side to side.
أو ننتقل من جانب إلى آخر.
Many of us do this, and sometimes
الكثير منا يفعل ذلك، وبعض الأحيان
it's an effort to soothe ourselves,
هي محاولة منا لتهدئة أنفسنا،
and I think in other animals that is often the case too.
و أعتقد أنه كذلك عند الحيوانات الأخرى في الغالب.
But it's not just stereotypic behaviors
ولكنها ليست السلوكيات النمطية فحسب
that other animals engage in.
التي تنخرط فيها الحيوانات الأخرى.
This is Gigi. She's a gorilla that lives
هذه هي جيجي. وهي غوريلا تعيش
at the Franklin Park Zoo in Boston.
في حديقة حيوانات فرانكلين في بوسطن.
She actually has a Harvard psychiatrist,
في الواقع، لديها طبيب نفساني من جامعة هارفارد
and she's been treated for a mood disorder
وكانت تعالج من اضطراب المزاج
among other things.
بالإضافة لبعض الأمور الأخرى.
Many animals develop mood disorders.
الكثير من الحيوانات تعاني من اضطرابات المزاج.
Lots of creatures —
الكثير من المخلوقات
this horse is just one example —
هذا الحصان هو أحد الأمثلة
develop self-destructive behaviors.
يعاني من سلوكيات التدمير الذاتي.
They'll gnaw on things
قد تقضم أشياء
or do other things that may also soothe them,
أو تقوم بأشياء أخرى من باب التهدئة الذاتية
even if they're self-destructive,
حتى لو كانت تعد تدميراً ذاتياً،
which could be considered similar
والذي يمكن اعتباره مماثل
to the ways that some humans cut themselves.
للطريقة التي يستخدمها البشر لتهدئة أنفسهم.
Plucking.
النتف.
Turns out, if you have fur or feathers or skin,
تبين أنه لو كان لديك ريش أو فرو أو جلد،
you can pluck yourself compulsively,
فيمكنك نتف نفسك لا إراديا،
and some parrots actually have been studied
وقد تمت بالفعل دراسة بعض البغبغاوات
to better understand trichotillomania, or compulsive plucking in humans,
للوصول إلى فهم أفضل لهوس نتف الشعر، أو نتف الشعر الإلزامي لدى البشر
something that affects
وهو اضطراب يصيب
20 million Americans right now.
20 مليون أمريكي في الوقت الحالي.
Lab rats pluck themselves too.
وفئران التجارب تنتف وبرها أيضًا.
In them, it's called barbering.
وتوصف الحالة لديها بالحلاقة.
Canine veterans of conflicts of Iraq and Afghanistan
الكلاب المحاربة العائدة من العراق وأفغانستان تعود
are coming back with what's considered canine PTSD,
مصابة بما يعد اضطراب الكرب التالي للصدمة النفسية (PTSD)
and they're having a hard time reentering civilian life
وتعاني من صعوبة في العودة للحياة المدنية
when they come back from deployments.
بعد انتهاء مهمتها في الحرب.
They can be too scared to approach men with beards
فقد تفزع من الاقتراب من رجل ملتحي
or to hop into cars.
أو من ركوب السيارات.
I want to be careful and be clear, though.
ورغم ذلك أود أن أكون حذرة وواضحة.
I do not think that canine PTSD
لا أعتقد أن اضطراب ما بعد الصدمة الموجود لدى الكلاب
is the same as human PTSD.
تشبه تلك الموجودة لدى البشر.
But I also do not think that my PTSD
لكني أعتقد كذلك أن اضطرابي
is like your PTSD,
لا يشبه اضطرابك
or that my anxiety or that my sadness is like yours.
أو أن حزني وقلقي يشبه حزنك وقلقك.
We are all different.
كلنا مختلفون.
We also all have very different susceptibilities.
كما أن لدينا قابليات مختلفة.
So two dogs, raised in the same household,
حيث أن كلبان يقيمان في ذات المنزل
exposed to the very same things,
ويتعرضان لذات الأمور،
one may develop, say, a debilitating fear of motorcycles,
أحدهما قد يصاب بخوف من الدراجات الهوائية،
or a phobia of the beep of the microwave,
أو رهاب من جرس جهاز المايكروويف،
and another one is going to be just fine.
في حين قد لا يصاب الآخر بشيء.
So one thing that people ask me pretty frequently:
أحد أكثر الأسئلة المطروحة عليّ:
Is this just an instance of humans
هل هذا مثال على أن البشر
driving other animals crazy?
يقودون الحيوانات للجنون؟
Or, is animal mental illness just a result of mistreatment or abuse?
أو هل المرض النفسي الحيواني ينتج عن سوء المعاملة؟
And it turns out we're actually
و يتبين أننا في الواقع
so much more complicated than that.
أكثر تعقيداً من ذلك.
So one great thing that has happened to me
من أعظم الأمور التي وقعت لي
is recently I published a book on this,
هو نشري لكتاب يتناول هذا الموضوع.
and every day now that I open my email
وكل يوم أتفقد فيه بريدي الإلكتروني
or when I go to a reading
أو عندما أحضر محاضرة
or even when I go to a cocktail party,
أو حتى عندما أحضر حفلة كوكتيل
people tell me their stories
يخبرني الناس عن قصص
of the animals that they have met.
حول الحيوانات التي التقوا بها.
And recently, I did a reading in California,
ومؤخراً، عقدت محاضرة في كاليفورنيا
and a woman raised her hand after the talk and she said,
ورفعت امرأة يدها بعد الحديث وقالت:
"Dr. Braitman, I think my cat has PTSD."
"د.بريتمان أعتقد أن قطتي مصابة باضطرابات ما بعد الصدمة
And I said, "Well, why? Tell me a little bit about it."
فقل:"لماذا؟ حدثيني بالمزيد عن الحالة."
So, Ping is her cat. She was a rescue,
بينغ هو اسم قطتها، وكانت مُنقذَة.
and she used to live with an elderly man,
كانت تقيم مع رجل مسن،
and one day the man was vacuuming
كان الرجل يكنس في أحد الأيام،
and he suffered a heart attack, and he died.
وتعرض لنوبة قلبية ولقى نحبه.
A week later, Ping was discovered in the apartment
بعد أسبوع، تم العثور على بينغ في الشقة
alongside the body of her owner,
إلى جانب جثة مالكها،
and the vacuum had been running the entire time.
وكانت المكنسة تعمل طوال الوقت.
For many months, up to I think two years after that incident,
ولعدة أشهر، حتى عامين من الحادث كما أظن،
she was so scared she couldn't be in the house when anyone was cleaning.
كانت تعاني من الذعر ولم تكن قادرة على التواجد في البيت خلال تنظيمه.
She was quite literally a scaredy cat.
كانت قطة هلوعة للغاية.
She would hide in the closet.
فكانت تختبئ في الخزانة.
She was un-self-confident and shaky,
كانت مهزوزة وغير واثقة من نفسها.
but with the loving support of her family,
ولكن مع الدعم الذي تلقته من عائلتها،
a lot of a time, and their patience,
والوقت المكرس لها، وصبرهم،
now, three years later,
الآن، وبعد ثلاث سنوات،
she's actually a happy, confident cat.
أصبحت قطة سعيدة وواثقة من نفسها.
Another story of trauma and recovery that I came across
ومن قصص الصدمات والتعافي التي صادفتها
was actually a few years ago.
وقعت منذ سنوات قليلة.
I was in Thailand to do some research.
كنت في تايلاند لإجراء بعض الأبحاث.
I met a monkey named Boonlua,
التقيت بقرد يدعى بونلوا،
and when Boonlua was a baby,
وحينما كان بونلوا طفلاً،
he was attacked by a pack of dogs,
هاجمه قطيع من الكلاب،
and they ripped off both of his legs and one arm,
ومزقوا ساقيه الاثنتين وذراعه،
and Boonlua dragged himself to a monastery,
فأخذ بونلوا يجر نفسه حتى وصل إلى دير
where the monks took him in.
حيث أدخله الرهبان.
They called in a veterinarian, who treated his wounds.
استدعوا بدورهم طبيبًا بيطريًّا تولى علاجه.
Eventually, Boonlua wound up
في النهاية، انتهى الحال
at an elephant facility,
بالقرد في منشأة للفيلة
and the keepers really decided to take him under their wing,
وقرر المربون أن يتعهدوه بالرعاية،
and they figured out what he liked,
وقد عرفوا ما كان يحبه،
which, it turned out, was mint Mentos
واتضح أنه كان يحب حلوى النعناع
and Rhinoceros beetles and eggs.
والخنافس وحيدة القرن والبيض.
But they worried, because he was social, that he was lonely,
لكنهم كانوا قلقين لكونه كان وحيدًا،
and they didn't want to put him in with another monkey,
ولم يكونوا يرغبون بوضعه مع قرد آخر
because they thought with just one arm,
لأنهم كانوا يعتقدون أنه بذراع واحدة
he wouldn't be able to defend himself or even play.
لن يتمكن من الدفاع عن نفسه أو حتى اللعب.
And so they gave him a rabbit,
فأعطوه أرنبًا،
and Boonlua was immediately a different monkey.
فتغير بونلوا تغيرًا كبيرًا.
He was extremely happy to be with this rabbit.
كان في سعادة غامرة لمرافقته هذا الأرنب.
They groomed each other, they become close friends,
كانا يعتنيان ببعضهما، وأصبحا مقربيَن.
and then the rabbit had bunnies,
ثم أصبح للأرنب صغارًا،
and Boonlua was even happier than he was before,
فأصبح بونلوا أكثر سعادة من قبل
and it had in a way given him
حيث أعطاه ذلك
a reason to wake up in the morning,
سببًا للإستيقاظ صباحًا،
and in fact it gave him such a reason to wake up
وفي الواقع، أعطاه سببًا ليستقيظ
that he decided not to sleep.
حتى أنه قرر ألا ينام.
He became extremely protective of these bunnies,
لقد أصبح حاميًا لتلك الأرانب الصغيرة،
and he stopped sleeping,
فكان يمتنع عن النوم
and he would sort of nod off
وكان يغفى أحيانًا
while trying to take care of them.
وهو يعتني بها.
In fact, he was so protective and so affectionate
في الواقع، كان حنونًا وحاميًا
with these babies that the sanctuary
لأولئك الصغار حتى أن الملجأ
eventually had to take them away from him
اضطر أخيرًا لأن يأخذوهم منه
because he was so protective, he was worried
لأنه كان يبالغ في حمايتها، فكان قلقًا
that their mother might hurt them.
من أن أمهم قد تؤذيهم.
So after they were taken away, the sanctuary staff
وبعد أن أخذوا الصغار منه،
worried that he would fall into a depression,
قلق طاقم الملجأ من تعرضه للإكتئاب،
and so to avoid that,
ولتفادي ذلك،
they gave him another rabbit friend.
أعطاه الطاقم أرنبًا مصاحبًا آخر.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
My official opinion is that he does not look depressed.
رأيي أنه لا يبدو مكتئبًا.
So one thing that I would really like people to feel
من الأمور التي أود أن يشعر بها الناس
is that you really should feel empowered
هو أنه ينبغي أن تشعروا بقدرتكم
to make some assumptions
على افتراض بعض الافتراضات
about the creatures that you know well.
حول المخلوقات التي تعرفونها جيدًا.
So when it comes to your dog
فعندما يتعلق الأمر بكلبك
or your cat or maybe your one-armed monkey
أو قطتك أو حتى قردك ذو الذراع الواحدة
that you happen to know,
الذين قُدر لك معرفته،
if you think that they are traumatized or depressed,
لو اعتقدت أنهم قد يكونوا أصيبوا بصدمات أو بالاكتئاب،
you're probably right.
فأنت محق على الأرجح.
This is extremely anthropomorphic,
وهذا تجسيد مبالغ فيه،
or the assignation of human characteristics
أو نسب السمات البشرية
onto non-human animals or things.
على ماهو غير بشري من حيوانات وأشياء.
I don't think, though, that that's a problem.
ولا أظن أن هذه مشكلة.
I don't think that we can not anthropomorphize.
لا أعتقد أننا نعجز عن تجسيدها
It's not as if you can take your human brain out of your head
وليس القصد إزالة الدماغ البشري من الرأس
and put it in a jar and then use it
ووضعه في جرة ثم استخدامه
to think about another animal thinking.
للتفكير في طريقة تفكير حيوان آخر.
We will always be one animal wondering
دائما سنكون حيوانًا يتسائل عن
about the emotional experience of another animal.
التجربة العاطفية لحيوانٍ آخر.
So then the choice becomes, how do you anthropomorphize well?
فيصبح الاختيار، كيف تجسد جيدًا؟
Or do you anthropomorphize poorly?
أو هل تجسد على نحو سئ؟
And anthropomorphizing poorly
والتجسيد السيء
is all too common.
شائع جدًّا.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
It may include dressing your corgis up and throwing them a wedding,
قد يتضمن ذلك تأنيق كلابك وأخذها إلى حفلة زفاف.
or getting too close to exotic wildlife because
أو الاقتراب من حياة برية غريبة
you believe that you had a spiritual connection.
لأنك تظن أنك تملك رابطا روحيا.
There's all manner of things.
هناك أنواع مختلفة من الأشياء.
Anthropomorphizing well, however, I believe is based
لكن التجسيد المتقن برأيي مبني على
on accepting our animal similarities with other species
تقبل متشابهاتنا الحيوانية مع الكائنات الأخرى
and using them to make assumptions
واستعمالها لصنع الافتراضات
that are informed about other animals' minds and experiences,
حول عقول الحيوانات الأخرى وتجاربها،
and there's actually an entire industry
ويوجد في الواقع مجال كامل
that is in some ways based on anthropomorphizing well,
قائم بطريقة ما على التجسيد الجيد.
and that is the psychopharmaceutical industry.
وهو مجال علم النفس الدوائي.
One in five Americans is currently taking a psychopharmaceutical drug,
يتعاطى واحد من خمسة أمريكيين دواءً نفسيًّا،
from the antidepressants and antianxiety medications
بدءًا بمضادات الاكتئاب والقلق
to the antipsychotics.
وصولاً إلى مضادات الذهان.
It turns out that we owe this
تبين أننا ندين
entire psychopharmaceutical arsenal
بهذه الترسانة من الأدوية النفسية
to other animals.
إلى الحيوانات الأخرى.
These drugs were tested in non-human animals first,
جُربت تلك العقاقير على الحيوانات غير البشرية أولاً
and not just for toxicity but for behavioral effects.
ليس فقط لاختبار الأثار الجانية بل لاختبار الآثار السلوكية أيضًا.
The very popular antipsychotic Thorazine
مضاد الذهان الشائع، ثورازين
first relaxed rats before it relaxed people.
هدّأ الفئران قبل أن يهدئ البشر.
The antianxiety medication Librium
ومضادات القلق ليبريوم
was given to cats selected for their meanness in the 1950s
أعطي لقطط اختيرت لشدة خبثها في خمسينات القرن الثامن عشر
and made them into peaceable felines.
وحولتها إلى هرر مسالمة.
And even antidepressants were first tested in rabbits.
وحتى مضادات الاكتئاب اختبرت أولا على الأرانب.
Today, however, we are not just giving these drugs
واليوم، نحن لا نعطي تلك العقاقير
to other animals as test subjects,
للحيوانات الأخرى كعينات إختبار،
but they're giving them these drugs as patients,
بل تُعطى العقاقير باعتبارها حيوانات مريضة،
both in ethical and much less ethical ways.
بطرق أخلاقية وأخرى أقل أخلاقية على حدٍّ سواء
SeaWorld gives mother orcas antianxiety medications
تعطي شركة SeaWorld الحيتان القاتلة مضادات القلق
when their calves are taken away.
حينما تؤخذ منها صغارها.
Many zoo gorillas have been given antipsychotics
وأخذت العديد من حيوانات الغوريلا في حديقة الحيوان
and antianxiety medications.
مضادات الذهان والقلق.
But dogs like my own Oliver
ولكن الكلاب مثل كلبي أوليفر
are given antidepressants and some antianxiety medications
تعطى مضادات الإكتئاب وبعض مضادات القلق
to keep them from jumping out of buildings
لمنعها من القفز من المباني
or jumping into traffic.
أو القفز وسط حركة السير.
Just recently, actually, a study came out in "Science"
ومؤخرًا نُشرت دراسة في مجلة Science
that showed that even crawdads
أظهرت أنه حتى جراد البحر
responded to antianxiety medication.
استجاب لمضاد القلق.
It made them braver, less skittish,
لقد جعله أكثر شجاعة وأقل جفولًا،
and more likely to explore their environment.
وأصبح أكثر عرضة لاكتشاف بيئته.
It's hard to know how many animals are on these drugs,
يصعب معرفة عدد الحيوانات التي تتعاطى هذه الأدوية،
but I can tell you that the animal pharmaceutical industry
ولكن يمكنني إخباركم أن قطاع الأدوية النفسية الحيوانية
is immense and growing,
يعتبر أضخم قطاع وفي توسع،
from seven billion dollars in 2011
فمن 7 مليار دولار في 2011
to a projected 9.25 billion by the year 2015.
إلى 9,25 مليار تقريبا بحلول عام 2015.
Some animals are on these drugs indefinitely.
تتعاطى بعض الحيوانات تلك الأدوية إلى ما لا نهاية.
Others, like one bonobo who lives in Milwaukee
وأخرى، مثل قرد بونوبو يعيش في ميلواكي
at the zoo there was on them
في حديقة الحيوان، كان يتناولها
until he started to save his Paxil prescription
حتى بدأ في تخزين عقار باكسيل الخاص به
and then distribute it among the other bonobos.
وتوزيعه على قردة البونوبو الأخرى.
(Laughter) (Applause)
(ضحك) (تصفيق)
More than psychopharmaceuticals, though,
فإلى جانب لأدوية النفسية،
there are many, many, many other
توجد الكثير والكثير من
therapeutic interventions that help other creatures.
التدخلات العلاجية التي تساعد المخلوقات الأخرى.
And here is a place where I think actually
وهناك مجال حيث أعتقد حقًّا
that veterinary medicine can teach something
أن الطب البيطري يمكن أن يساهم معرفيًّا بشيء
to human medicine,
للطب البشري.
which is, if you take your dog, who is, say,
وهو، إن أخذت كلبك الذي، لنقل،
compulsively chasing his tail,
يطارد ذيله بصورة قهرية،
into the veterinary behaviorist,
إلى معالج سلوكي بيطري،
their first action isn't to reach for the prescription pad;
فإن تصرفه الأول لن يكون تناول دفتر الوصفات الطبية،
it's to ask you about your dog's life.
بل سيكون سؤالك عن حياة كلبك.
They want to know how often your dog gets outside.
يريد أن يعرف كم مرة يتنزه فيها كلبك خارجًا.
They want to know how much exercise your dog is getting.
يريد معرفة مقدار ما يمارسه كلبك من تمارين.
They want to know how much social time
يريد معرفة مقدار وقته المقضي
with other dogs and other humans.
في الاجتماع مع الكلاب الأخرى والبشر الآخرين.
They want to talk to you about what sorts of therapies,
يريد أن يتحدث إليك بشأن أنواع العلاج
largely behavior therapies,
أنواع العلاج السلوكي
you've tried with that animal.
التي جربتها مع ذلك الحيوان.
Those are the things that often tend to help the most,
هذه الأمور هي أكثر ما يحدث الفرق،
especially when combined with psychopharmaceuticals.
لا سيما إن دُمجت مع الأدوية النفسية.
The thing, though, I believe, that helps the most,
لكن أكثر ما يساعد بنظري،
particularly with social animals,
وخاصة مع الحيوانات الإجتماعية،
is time with other social animals.
هو قضاء الوقت مع الحيوانات الإجتماعية الأخرى.
In many ways, I feel like I became a service animal
بعدة أشكال، أشعر أني أصبحت مقدم مساعدة للحيوان
to my own dog,
لكلبي.
and I have seen parrots do it for people
ورأيت ببغاوات تصاحب بشرًا
and people do it for parrots
وبشر يصاحبون ببغاوات
and dogs do it for elephants
وكلاب تصاحب فيلة
and elephants do it for other elephants.
وفيلة تصاحب فيلة أخرى.
I don't know about you;
لا أعلم بشأنكم.
I get a lot of Internet forwards
لكني أتلقى إفادات كثيرة عبر الإنترنت
of unlikely animal friendships.
حول صداقات حيوانية غير محتملة.
I also think it's a huge part of Facebook,
كما أعتقد أنها تحتل جزء كبير من الفايسبوك،
the monkey that adopts the cat
كالقرد الذي يتبنى قطة،
or the great dane who adopted the orphaned fawn,
أو الكلب الدنماركي الذي تبنى ولد ظبي يتيم،
or the cow that makes friends with the pig,
أو البقرة التي تصادق خنزيرًا،
and had you asked me eight, nine years ago, about these,
ولو سألتموني عن هذه الصداقات منذ 9 سنوات
I would have told you that they were hopelessly sentimental
لأخبرتكم أنها كانت عاطفية تمامًا
and maybe too anthropomorphic in the wrong way
وربما كانت تجسيدية على نحوٍ خاطئ
and maybe even staged, and what I can tell you now
وربما أيضًا منظمة، وما يمكنني أن أخبركم به الآن
is that there is actually something to this.
أنه في الواقع يوجد شيء من هذا القبيل.
This is legit. In fact, some interesting studies
هذا شرعي. في الواقع، بعض الدراسات المثيرة
have pointed to oxytocin levels,
أشارت إلى مستويات هرمون أوكسيتوسين،
which are a kind of bonding hormone
المعروف بهرمون الحب
that we release when we're having sex or nursing
الذي يُطلق أثناء الجماع أو الاحتضان
or around someone that we care for extremely,
أو التواجد حول شخص نهتم به للغاية،
oxytocin levels raising in both humans and dogs
ترتفع مستويات أوكسيتوسين في البشر والكلاب
who care about each other
الذين يعتنون ببعضهم البعض
or who enjoy each other's company,
أو الذي يستمتعون برفقة بعضهم البعض،
and beyond that, other studies show that oxytocin
وأكثر من ذلك، تظهر بعض الدراسات أن الأوكسيتوسين
raised even in other pairs of animals,
ارتفع حتى في أزواج الحيوانات الأخرى،
so, say, in goats and dogs who were friends and played with each other,
لنقل لدى المعز والكلاب الذين كانوا أصدقاء ويلعبون مع بعضهم البعض،
their levels spiked afterwards.
ارتفع مستوى الهرمون ارتفاع كبير بعد ذلك.
I have a friend who really showed me that
لدي صديق أظهر لي بالفعل
mental health is in fact a two-way street.
أن الصحة النفسية لها اتجاهان.
His name is Lonnie Hodge, and he's a veteran of Vietnam.
اسمه لوني هودج، وهو من محاربي فيتنام القدامى.
When he returned, he started working
عندما عاد، بدأ يعمل
with survivors of genocide and a lot of people
مع الناجين من الإبادة والكثير من الناس
who had gone through war trauma.
الذين عانوا من صدمات نفسية.
And he had PTSD and also a fear of heights,
كان يعاني من الكرب التالي للصدمة، وكذلك رهاب المرتفعات
because in Vietnam, he had been
لأنه كان في فيتنام
rappelling backwards out of helicopters
يهبط من الطائرات المروحية
over the skids,
عبر المزالق،
and he was givena service dog named Gander, a labradoodle,
وقد مُنح كلب مساعد اسمه غاندر، من فصيلة Labradoodle
to help him with PTSD and his fear of heights.
لمساعدته مع اضطرابه وخوفه من المرتفعات.
This is them actually on the first day that they met,
وهاهما في أول يوم التقيا فيه،
which is amazing, and since then,
وهذا مذهل، ومنذ ذلك الحين،
they've spent a lot of time together
قضيا وقتًا طويلًا برفقة بعضهما
visiting with other veterans suffering from similar issues.
لزيارة محاربين قدامى آخرين يعانون من مشاكل مشابهة.
But what's so interesting to me about Lonnie and Gander's relationship
ولكن ما أثار اهتمامي حول علاقة لوني وغاندر
is about a few months in,
هو أنه بعد أشهر قليلة من العلاقة،
Gander actually developed a fear of heights,
أُصيب غاندر برهاب المرتفعات،
probably because he was watching Lonnie so closely.
ربما لأنه كان يراقب لوني عن كثب.
What's pretty great about this, though, is that he's still a fantastic service dog,
وما يثير الدهشة أن لا يزال مع ذلك كلب مساعد رائع،
because now, when they're both at a great height,
لأنه الآن، عندما يكونان على مرتفع كبير،
Lonnie is so concerned with Gander's well-being
يقلق لوني على سلامة غاندر
that he forgets to be scared of the heights himself.
فينسى أنه نفسه يخشى المرتفعات.
Since I've spent so much time with these stories,
وبما أنني قضيت وقتًا طويلًا مع تلك القصص،
digging into archives,
من خلال غوصي في السجلات،
I literally spent years doing this research,
قضيت سنوات لإجراء هذا البحث،
and it's changed me.
وقد غيّرني.
I no longer look at animals at the species level.
لم أعد أنظر للحيوانات على مستوى الأنواع،
I look at them as individuals,
بل أنظر لها باعتبارها أفرادُا،
and I think about them as creatures
وأبحث فيها باعتبارها مخلوقات
with their own individual weather systems
تملك أنظمة الطقس الفردية الخاصة بها
guiding their behavior and informing
التي توجه سلوكها وتعكس
how they respond to the world.
استجابتها للعالم.
And I really believe that this has made me
وأعتقد أن ذلك جعلني
a more curious and a more empathetic person,
أكثر حبًّا للاستطلاع وأكثر عاطفة،
both to the animals that share my bed
تجاه الحيوانات التي تشاركني فراشي
and occasionally wind up on my plate,
وينتهي الحال بها في صحني،
but also to the people that I know
وأيضًا تجاه الأشخاص الذين أعرف
who are suffering from anxiety
بشأن معاناتهم من القلق
and from phobias and all manner of other things,
والرهاب والإضطرابات الأخرى من كل نوع،
and I really do believe that
وأعتقد حقًّا أنه
even though you can't know exactly
رغم أنك تعجز عن معرفة
what's going on in the mind of a pig
ما يجري داخل دماغ الخنزير
or your pug or your partner,
أو كلبك أو شريكك،
that that shouldn't stop you from empathizing with them.
فإن ذلك لا ينبغي أن يمنعكم من التعاطف معها.
The best thing that we could do for our loved ones
أفضل ما يمكننا فعله مع من نحبهم.
is, perhaps, to anthropomorphize them.
هو في الحقيقة تجسيدهم
Charles Darwin's father once told him
والد تشارلز داروين قال له مرة
that everybody could lose their mind at some point.
أن الجميع يمكن أن يفقد عقله بدرجة ما.
Thankfully, we can often find them again,
والحمد لله يمكننا استعادة عقولنا مرة أخرى،
but only with each other's help.
ولكن فقط بمساعدة الآخر.
Thank you.
شكراً لكم
(Applause)
(تصفيق)